# Cristóbal Sifón

Profesor Auxiliar Instituto de Física, Facultad de Ciencias Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso Casilla 4059, Valparaíso, Chile

E-mail: cristobal.sifon@pucv.cl Phone: +56 (32) 227 4698

https://github.com/cristobal-sifon/

#### Research Interests

My research focuses on galaxy cluster physics including observable—mass scaling relations for cosmological analyses and the transformation of galaxies in and around galaxy clusters. I am also interested in intrinsic galaxy alignments, both as contaminants for cosmic shear and as a physical mechanism in their own right. I use various tools and techniques to study these phenomena, including weak gravitational lensing, spectroscopy, the exploitation of optical surveys in general, and most recently also of hydrodynamical simulations.

**Collaborations:** 4MOST Chilean Cluster Galaxy Evolution Survey (CHANCES) — 4MOST Hemisphere Survey (4HS) — Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT) — Canadian Cluster Comparison Project (CCCP) — Cerro Chajnator Atacama Telescope (CCAT) — CMB-S4 — Galaxy Cluster Mass Reconstruction Project — Kilo-Degree Survey (KiDS) — Legacy Survey of Space and Time Dark Energy Science Collaboration (LSST-DESC) — Multi-Epoch Nearby Cluster Survey (MENeaCS) — Simons Observatory.

# **Employment**

[2022 - Present] Profesor Auxiliar, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso (PUCV), Chile

[2019 - 2022] Profesor Asociado, PUCV

[2016 - 2019] Postdoctoral Research Associate, Princeton University, USA

### **Education**

[2012 - 2016] Ph.D. Astrophysics, Universiteit Leiden, The Netherlands

[2010 - 2012] M.Sc. Astrophysics, P. Universidad Católica de Chile (PUC), Chile

[2005 - 2010] B.Sc. Astronomy, PUC

# **Teaching & Mentoring**

# **Graduate Research Mentoring**

[2023 - Present] Javier Urrutia, PUCV: MSc thesis advisor.

[2020 - 2022] Camila Aros, PUCV: MSc thesis advisor.

[2017 – 2019] Naomi Robertson, Oxford University (UK): co-advised PhD thesis project (Advisor: Joanna Dunkley).

[2013 – 2014] Joshua Albert, Universiteit Leiden: co-advised MSc thesis project (Advisor: Huub Röttgering).

### **Undergraduate Research Mentoring**

[PUCV] 3 Senior theses and 4 Summer projects.

[Princeton] Summer project and Junior project.

[Others] Four-month research project through the Central American-Caribbean Bridge in Astrophysics (URL).

### **Courses Taught**

**Graduate:** Data Analysis (2023), Techniques of Observational Astrophysics (2022), Observational Cosmology (2020-2021)

Undergraduate: Introductory Astornomy (2024), Astronomical Instrumentation (2023), Galactic Astronomy

(2021-2022), Programming (2020-2022), Cosmology (2020) **Non-Physics Major:** Basic Astronomy for Engineers (2022)

## **Grants**

[2020] ALMA-ANID Fund to hire a postdoc (Co-PI, 2 years, US\$77,000) [2019] FONDECYT Iniciación research grant (PI, 3 years, US\$125,000)

# Successful Observing Proposals (as PI)

I have been the PI of 17 successful observing proposals totalling hundreds of observing hours in optical (VLT/MUSE, Gemini-South/GMOS, VST/OmegaCAM, Blanco/DECam), near-infrared (Magellan/Fourstar, Blanco/NEWFIRM), submm (APEX/CONCERTO), and radio (GMRT, VLA) telescopes.

**Observing Experience:** I have spent roughly 180 hours observing with optical (Gemini South/GMOS) and near-infrared (NTT/Sofl, Blanco/NEWFIRM, Magellan/Fourstar) instruments performing both imaging and spectroscopy of galaxy clusters.

# **Community Activity**

**Journals:** I have served as a referee for Astronomy & Astrophysics, The Astrophysical Journal, Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, and Nature Astronomy.

**Telescope Allocation Committees:** Canadian Astronomical Society, *Chandra* X-ray Observatory **Grant Allocation Committees:** Swiss National Science Foundation, Chilean National Agency for Research and Development (ANID)

#### **Press Articles Authored**

[July 2017] Galaxy clusters: Falling into line (Nature Astronomy News & Views)

[July 2013] Featured Science: Dynamical masses of galaxy clusters discovered with the Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect (Gemini Focus)

#### Outreach

[Nov. 2023] Guest in "Diálogos Cósmicos" podcast (in Spanish, available here).

[Aug. 2023] Guest in "Conversemos de Astronomía" podcast (in Spanish, available here).

[Nov. 2022] Guest in "Rockstars" podcast by Radio TXS (in Spanish, available here).

[Oct. 2022] Interview for Radio Valentín Letelier, Valparaíso, to talk about CHANCES.

[Mar. 2021] Online public talk in the conext of the Chilean Day of Astronomy (in Spanish, available here).

[2018 - 2019] Assisted with Public Astronomical Observations in Spanish, Princeton University.

[2013 - 2014] Assisted with Public Observations at the Old Observatory, Leiden Observatory.

[2012] Co-taught an Astronomy Course for Seniors, PUC.

[2011] Participated in *Starry Nights*, observation nights for elementary and middle school students in social risk organized by ESO-Santiago.

[2010] Invited talk on board the "FFG14 Almirante Latorre" Chilean Navy ship, Valparaíso, Chile.

[2010] The Universe, a series of talks for elementary school students in social risk organized by PUC.

# **Technical skills**

I am an experienced Python programmer and I have some familiarity with IDL and Julia. I wrote pygmos, a Python/PyRAF pipeline to reduce Gemini-GMOS spectra which is available here. I am one of the lead developers and maintainers of the galaxy-galaxy lensing pipeline used by the KiDS collaboration (written in Python, but which is not public at the moment). Other codes I have written are posted at my github page.

# Other Work Experience

[2020 - 2021] Data science & Machine Learning consultant, Minera Centinela, Chile.

[2007 – 2008] Ski instructor at Homewood Mountain Ski Resort in Lake Tahoe, CA, USA. Obtained certification as *Level I Ski Instructor* by the Professional Ski Instructors of America (PSIA).

[2006 - 2007] Ski lift operator at Sun Valley Resort, Sun Valley, ID, USA.

#### References

Prof. Henk Hoekstra (PhD advisor)
Leiden Observatory, Universiteit Leiden
Niels Bohrweg 2, NL-2333 CA Leiden, The Netherlands

Phone: +31 (71) 527 5594

E-mail: hoekstra@strw.leidenuniv.nl

Prof. John P. Hughes
Department of Physics and Astronomy, Rutgers University
136 Frelinghuysen Rd., Piscataway, NJ 08854, USA
Phone: +1 (848) 445 8878

E-mail: jph@physics.rutgers.edu

• Prof. Felipe Menanteau

Department of Astronomy, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign 1002 W. Green St., Urbana, IL 61801, USA

Phone: +1 (217) 244 6297 E-mail: felipe@illinois.edu

• Prof. David N. Spergel

Center for Computational Astrophysics, Flatiron Institute 160 Fifth Avenue, 7th Floor, New York, NY 10010, USA

Phone: +1 (646) 654 0066

E-mail: dns@astro.princeton.edu

Prof. L. Felipe Barrientos (MSc advisor)
Instituto de Astrofísica, P. Universidad Católica de Chile
Casilla 306, Santiago 22, Chile

Phone: +56 (2) 2354 4941

E-mail: barrientos@astro.uc.cl

# Selected recent publications (All including C. Sifón)

I have co-authored 141 scientific articles intended for peer-reviewed publication, including 8 first-author papers. They have been cited more than 8,400 times and have an h-index of 50, with more than 380 citations on my first-author papers. The full list of publications can be accessed at the SAO/NASA Astrophysics Data System. This document is maintained live on github.

- 13. M. Shirasaki, C. Sifón, et al. (15 co-authors), "Masses of Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Galaxy Clusters Detected by The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: Stacked Lensing Measurements with Subaru HSC Year 3 data" 2024, arXiv:2407.08201, submitted to Phys. Rev. D
- 12. C. Sifón, J. Han, "The history and mass content of cluster galaxies in the EAGLE simulation", 2024, A&A, 686, A163, [arXiv]
- 11. N. C. Robertson, C. Sifón, and 23 colleagues, "ACT-DR5 Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Clusters: Weak Lensing Mass Calibration with KiDS", 2024, A&A, 681, 87 [arXiv]
- 10. W. Coulton, and 153 colleagues, "Atacama Cosmology Telescope: High-resolution component-separated maps across one third of the sky", 2024, Phys. Rev. D, 109, 063530 [arXiv]
- 9. M. S. Madhavacheril, and 158 colleagues, "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: DR6 Gravitational Lensing Map and Cosmological Parameters", 2024, ApJ, 962, 113 [arXiv]
- 8. F. J. Qu, and 157 colleagues, "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: A Measurement of the DR6 CMB Lensing Power Spectrum and Its Implications for Structure Growth", 2024, ApJ, 962, 112 [arXiv]
- 7. Dark Energy Survey Kilo-Degree Survey Collaboration, and 160 colleagues, "DES Y3 + KiDS-1000: Consistent cosmology combining cosmic shear surveys", 2023, The Open Journal of Astrophysics, 6, 36 [arXiv]
- 6. M. Hilton, C. Sifón, and 133 colleagues "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: a Catalog of >4000 Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Galaxy Clusters", 2021, ApJS, 253, 3 [arXiv]
- 5. M. Aguena, and 24 colleagues, "CLMM: a LSST-DESC cluster weak lensing mass modeling library for cosmology", 2021, MNRAS, 508, 6092 [arXiv]
- J. Kim, M. J. Jee, J. P. Hughes, M. Yoon, K. HyeongHan, F. Menanteau, C. Sifón, L. Hovey, and P. Arunachalam, "Head-to-Toe Measurement of El Gordo: Improved Analysis of the Galaxy Cluster ACT-CL J0102-4915 with New Wide-Field Hubble Space Telescope Imaging Data", 2021, ApJ, 923, 101 [arXiv]
- 3. M. Mallaby-Kay, and 59 colleagues, "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: Summary of DR4 and DR5 Data Products and Data Access", 2021, ApJS, 255, 11 [arXiv]
- 2. M. S. Madhavacheril, C. Sifón, and 61 colleagues "The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: Weighing Distant Clusters with the Most Ancient Light", 2020, ApJL, 903, 13 [arXiv]
- R. Herbonnet, C. Sifón, H. Hoekstra, Y. Bahé, R. F. J. van der Burg, J.-B. Melin, A. von der Linden, D. Sand, S. Kay, D. Barnes, "CCCP and MENeaCS: (Updated) Weak-Lensing Masses for 100 Galaxy Clusters", 2020, MNRAS, 497, 4684 [arXiv]